Palestine Statehood Committee "Concerning the campaigns for a Jewish Army; to save the Jewish people of Europe and the establishment of a Hebrew Republic in Palestine" Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Microfilm of records in original order
  Before transferring the Palenstine Statehood Committee records to Yale in 1978, the Institute for Mediterranean Affairs (the body that assmbled records in this collection) microfilmed their holdings. Yale University Library then processed these records, thereby changing their order, and microfilmed them. Thus, the records in this series duplicate information in series I - III. This series may be interesting to researchers hoping to understand the diverging recordkeeping practices of the Institute for Mediterranean Affairs and the five committees whose records constitute this collection -- the American Friends of a Jewish Palestine, the Committee for an Army of Stateless and Palestinian Jews, the Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, the American League for a Free Palestine, and the Hebrew Committee of National Liberation. Series IV -- advertisements and clippings from The Answer -- were not re-microfilmed and are described only in series IV.
  - Committee files, general, 1938 - 1944 March (Box 20)
  - Committee files, general, 1944 - 1946 September (Box 21)
  - Committee files, general, 1944 June - August (Box 22)
  - Committee files, general, 1944 August - 1947 February (Box 23)
  - Committee files, general, 1946 October - 1947 July (Box 24)
  - Committee files, general, 1947 August - December (Box 25)
  - Committee for a Jewish Army brochures (Box 25)
  - Emergency Conference to Save the Jewish People of Europe printed matter (Box 25)
  - Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe printed matter (Box 25)
  - American Friends of a Jewish Palestine printed matter (Box 25)
  - American League for a Free Palestine printed matter (Box 25)
  - American League for a Free Palestine national convention printed matter, 1947 February 8 - 9 (Box 25)
  - Committee files, general, 1947 December - 1948 October (Box 26)
  - Subject files
    - Vladimir Jabotinsky (Box 27)
    - Hebrew Underground (Box 27)
    - Menachem Beigin (Box 27)
    - Altalena (Box 27)
    - Tyre Shipping Company (Box 27)
  - Committee files, general, 1948 August - 1949 (Box 27)
  - Advertisements -- American League for a Free Palestine and Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe (Box 28)
  - Subject files
    - Peter H. Bergson (Box 28)
    - Hebrews and Jews (Box 28)
    - Ben Hecht (Box 28)
    - Great Britain (Box 28)
    - Aryeh Ben Eliezer (Box 28)
    - Michel Berchin (Box 28)
    - Hebrew Underground (Box 28)
    - Committee for a Jewish Army newsletter, West Coast division (Box 29)
    - Repatriation (Af Al Pi); rescue (Box 29)
    - American Friends of a Jewish Palestine The Answer (Box 29)
    - Hebrew Committee of National Liberation activities in Great Britain (Box 29)
    - Hadani-Raffaeli (Box 29)
    - Obstructionists (Box 29)
  - Hebrew Committee of a National Liberation Bulletin (Box 29)
  - American League for a Free Palestine, Los Angeles correspondence, printed matter (Box 29)
  - Commonwealth (Box 29)
  - Small advertisements (Box 29)
  - Publications, A.L.F.P. and other committees (Box 30)
  - Subject files
    - Abrasha Stawsky (Box 30)
    - U.S. Department of State (Box 30)
    - Pierre van Paassen (Box 30)
    - "We Will Never Die" (Box 30)
    - Dramatis personae: clippings file on individuals (Box 30)
    - Hebrew Committee of National Liberation, Paris (Box 30)
    - Obstructionists (Box 30)
    - Samuel Merlin (Box 30)
    - Eri Jabotinsky (Box 30)
  - The Answer, 1945 (Box 31)
  - Clippings, misc. (Box 31)
  - Subject file: David Shapiro and Nathan Cohen, interviews (Box 31)
  - Pamphlets, misc. (Box 31)
  - Correspondence (duplicates of letters in the FDR Library and the Library of Congress) (Box 31)
  - Subject file: Sam and Betty Dubiner, interview (Box 31)
  - Lists of advertisements placed by the committees in newspapers, journals (Box 31)
  - Subject file: A Flag Is Born, 1946 (Box 31)
  - Committee for a Jewish Army: Memo (Box 31)
  - Subject file: "SS Ben Hecht" (Box 31)
  - Lists of mailings (Box 31)
  - Financial papers, 1945 (Box 31)
  - The Answer, 1943 April - 1946 September (Box 32)
- 1981 September Addition, 1939-1942
  These records are comprised of copies of records from two bodies. The first group include records from the UK Foreign Office, the originals of which are housed at the Public Record Office of the United Kingdom. The second group are copies of documents from the United States Department of State, collected from the National Archives of the United States. The content of these records reflect Samuel Merlin's research interests.
  - Public Record Office - Foreign Office
    Consists of copies of documents from the National Archives. Source numbers beginning CO and FO refer to National Archive document reference numbers.
    - Document 1. Walter [signature undecipherable] to Viscount Halifax (4 pages), 1939 September 29 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/23240 1779 No. 1114 193. Includes 1 attachment: Schwamm, Harvey to British Ambassador (2 pages), 1939 Sep 18 (source number: FO 371/23240 No. 195).
    - Document 2. American Friends of a Jewish Palestine to Malcolm MacDonald (4 pages), 1940 February 29 (cable) (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733 425/2 2735.
    - Document 3. Stanton, Willard to Halifax (3 pages), 1941 May 3 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/27127 5353. Includes 1 attachment: Bergson-Merlin to Abrahams, 1939 May 22.
    - Document 4. Walter to Lord Croft (2 pages), 1942 February 14 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 No. 76147 4818.
    - Document 5. Lord Wedgwood's speech (4 pages), 1942 February 25 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733-448 No. 76147 4818.
    - Document 6. Stephenson, Beryl to Mr. Thornley (7 pages), 1942 June 9 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 No. 76147 4818. Includes 1 attachment: Lord Croft's reply to Lord Wedgwood (6 pages).
    - Document 7. House of Lords, Lord Wedgwood and others (12 pages), 1942 June 9 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
    - Document 8. van Paassen, Pierre to Winston Churchill (3 pages), 1942 June 22 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/31379 5874.
    - Document 9. Washington to Foreign Office (4 pages), 1942 July 2 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
    - Document 10. British Embassy, Washington to Foreign Office (1 page), 1942 July 4 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/31379 5874. Consists of covering letters enclosing Pierre van Paassen's letter.
    - Document 11. British Embassy, Washington to Foreign Office (1 page), 1942 July 7 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
    - Document 12. Halifax to Alfred Strelsin (1 page), 1942 October 24 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 76147-A.
    - Document 13. Keane, Betty, New York to Jeremiah Halperin (1 page), 1942 October 27 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 76147-1A 4818.
    - Document 14. Halpern, J., London to H. Bergson, New York (3 pages), 1942 October 29 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
    - Document 15. re: Halpern letter to Bergson, 1942 November 4 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 76147-1A 4818. This letter was summarized and analyzed by the censor and sent to Thornley November 4, 1942. The censor also attached 3 appendices.
    - Document 16. To Dr. Radcliffe Solomon, etc. (4 pages), 1942 November 5 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 76147-1A 4818
    - Document 17. W. S. to E. B. Boyd (2 pages), 1942 November 8 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 76147-1-A 4818. Contains an enclosure - "Towards a Jewish Army" by Captain Jeremiah Helpern.
    - Document 18. W. S. to E. B. Boyd (17 pages), 1942 November 14 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 76147/1A 4818.
    - Document 19. Kellar, A. K. to A. H. Lincoln (18 pages), 1942 November 17 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      See also: Document 24.
      Source number: CO 733/448 76147/1A 4818. Contains an enclosure - 17 page report, "Memorandum on the Anglo-American Committee for a Jewish Army." Second draft attached (13 pages), source number: FO 371/31380 No. 6 4932.
    - Document 20. W. S. to Colonel Rolleston (2 pages), 1942 November 19 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
    - Document 21. Foreign Office to Washington (1 page), 1942 November 22 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
    - Document 22. Eden, Anthony to Viscount Cranborne (1 page), 1942 November 22 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
    - Document 23. Submitted on behalf of the British Section of the Anglo-American Committee for a Jewish Army, London (5 pages), 1942 November 26 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 76147/1A.
    - Document 24. War Office (17 pages), 1942 December 10 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      See also: Document 19.
    - Document 25
      - Street, A. W. to G. W. Baxter (1 page), 1942 December 14 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
        Source number: FO 371/31380 No. 6 4932. Includes 17 attachments.
      - Low, W. W. to Major Cowan (1 page), 1942 December 15 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
        Source number: FO 371/31380 No. 6 4932.
      - Lieutenant General Ismay to Mrs. Fitzpatrick (1 page), 1942 December 10 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
        Source number: CO 733/448/76147/1A 134194. 6. 31.
      - Fitzpatrick, M. to Ismay (1 page), 1942 November 27 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      - Memorandum on greater utilization of Jewish Manpower (5 pages), 1942 November 26 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
        Source number: FO 371/31380 #160
      - Some Information regarding the "Anglo-American" Committee for a Jewish Army (4 pages), 1942 October 12 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
        Source number: FO 371/31380 #4932 #155.
      - Some Information regarding the "Anglo-American" Committee for a Jewish Army (5 pages), 1942 October 12 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
        Source number: CO 733/448 76147/1A 4818. Duplicate copy not filmed.
    - Document 26. To Viscount Halifax (3 pages), 1942 December 23 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
    - Document 27. Kellar, A. J. to A. H. Lincoln (9 pages, missing), 1942 December 28 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 76147/1A 4818. Contains enclosures: A Proclamation on the Moral Rights of the Stateless and Palestinian Jews.
    - Document 27a. Helpern, Captain J. to Rt. Hon. R. G. Casey (2 pages), 1942 December 28 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: CO 733/448 26147/1A 4818. Includes 1 attachment: 1942 Dec 30 letter to E. B. Boyd.
    - Document 28. Halifax to Anthony Eden (6 pages), 1943 January 15 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/35031 5919. Regards response to agitation for formation of a separate Jewish military force.
    - Document 29. Jabotinsky, Eri to J. M. Dayag, Jerusalem (5 pages), 1943 September 4 (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40129 No. 67 5942. The censor's indignant note attached (1943 Nov 2).
    - Document 30. British Embassy, Washington to Foreign Office (1 page), 1943 September 9 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/35038 No. 87 4966z.
    - Document 31. British Embassy, Washington to Foreign Office (1 page), 1943 September 15 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/35032 No. 87 4966.
    - Document 32. Wright, Michael to Foreign Office (2 pages), 1943 October 14 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/35040 4965. Consists of 1 enclosure: Jewish Group in Opposition to Proposal for "Ghetto" Army.
    - Document 33. Abrahams, A. to L. Altman, Jerusalem (5 pages), 1943 November 4 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/35042 4989. Regards Palestine censorship.
    - Document 34. Wright, Michael to C. W. Baxter (6 pages), 1944 May 15 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40131 5940. Includes 2 attachments: Chancery to Registrar, 1944 May 24; Washington to Foreign Office, 1944 May 24.
    - Document 35. Washington, Viscount Halifax to Foreign Office (3 pages), 1944 May 19 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40131 5940.
    - Document 36. New York Times (1 page), 1944 June 17 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40131 5940. National Liberation Committee registers as a foreign agent.
    - Document 37. JTA (1 page), 1944 June 23 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40131 5940. Consists of N.Z.O. refusal to support Hebrew Liberation Committee leads to split in party.
    - Document 38. Organization, Johannesburg to Lord Strabolgi (1 page), 1944 July 15 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40144 No. 628 5066.
    - Document 39. Halifax to Anthony Eden (10 pages), 1944 October 20 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40132 2908. Consists of 9 attachments regarding attacks on Peter Bergson in the Washington Post.
    - Document 40. Bergsen, Peter to Captain J. Halpern (5 pages), 1944 October 21 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40132 2908.
    - Document 41. Cooper, Duff (2 pages), 1944 October 22 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40146 #628 5082. Regards J. Halpern's instructions to visit Paris to see General de Gaulle about Jews fighting for the Allies.
    - Document 42. A. to S. of S. (1 page), 1944 November 9 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      No source number, regards partition.
    - Document 43. Butler, M. to Secretary of State (1 page), 1944 November 9 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45376 8479. Regards partition.
    - Document 44. Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (8 pages), 1944 November 9 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 45. re: Partition (2 pages), 1944 November 15 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45376 8479.
    - Document 46. Wright, Michael to Foreign Office (2 pages), 1944 November 20 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/40132 2908. Contains 1 enclosure - Washington Post editorial on Peter Bergson Group dated 1944 Oct 13.
    - Document 47. re: The Stern Gang (1 page), 1944 November 22 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 48. re: The Stern Gang (1 page), 1944 November 22 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 49. Cadogan, S. A. (1 page), 1944 November 23 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 50. Thornley (?) to P. J. Dixon (7 pages), 1944 November 23 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45376 8479. Regards situation in Palestine.
    - Document 51. Hankey, R. M. A. (1 page), 1944 November 23 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 52. Hankey, R. M. A. (1 page), 1944 November 24 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 53. To Secretary of State (1 page), 1944 November 26, 27, 28 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 54. (1 page), 1944 November 28 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 54a. Brooke, A. F. to War Cabinet (1 page), 1944 November 28 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 55. Butler, M. to Sir Cadogan (2 pages), 1944 November 30 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45376 8479. Regards Lord Moyne.
    - Document 56. High Commissioner for Palestine and Trans-Jordan to Secretary of State (1 page), 1944 December 11 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45376 2747. Regard Eri Jabotinsky.
    - Document 57. Weizmann, Dr. Chaim to Prime Minister (1 page), 1944 December 18 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45376 84791.
    - Document 58. Gort, Viscount, Palestine to S. of S. Colonies (4 pages), 1944 December 30 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 59. Earl of Halifax to Foreign Office (2 pages), 1945 January 14 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45376 2747. Consists of a memo and note in Hebrew.
    - Document 60. Eastwood to R. M. A. Hankey (8 pages), 1945 January 17 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45376 8479. Consists of a 1 page memo and 7 page C. I. D. report.
    - Document 61. Butler, M. (3 pages), 1945 January 18 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 62. Butler, M. (1 page), 1945 January 19 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 63. Cornwallis, Sir K. to Mr. Eden (2 pages), 1945 January 19 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 64. Cornwallis, Sir K. to F. O. (2 pages), 1945 January 19 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 65. Ch. Weizmann to Sir Edward (1 page), 1945 January 25 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 66. Grigg, Edward to Prime Minister (1 page), 1945 January 27 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 67. Grigg, Edward to Winston Churchill (3 pages), 1945 January 27 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 68. Grigg, Edward to Winston Churchill (1 page), 1945 January 29 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 69. Hankey, R. M. A. to Sir E. Grigg, 1945 January 29 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 70. Grigg, E. to Anthony Eden (5 pages), 1945 January 29 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 71. Prime Minister to Mr. Lawford (1 page), 1945 January 31 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 72. Hankey, R. M. A. (2 pages), 1945 January 31 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45398 8385.
    - Document 73. Hankey, R. M. A. (4 pages), 1945 January 31 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 74. Wright to Hankey (1 page), 1945 January 31 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 75. From R. M. A. H. (1 page), 1945 January 31 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 76. Prime Minister to V. G. Lawford (1 page), 1945 February 1 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 77. A. E. to Prime Minister (1 page), 1945 February 2 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 78. From Churchill, Winston (1 page), 1945 February 2 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 79. From Lord Killearn (3 pages), 1945 February 5 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45398 8385. Includes two attachments.
    - Document 80. Eden to Resident Minister in Cairo (1 page), 1945 February 8 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 81. Grigg, Edward to Secretary of State (1 page), 1945 February 13 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 82. Eastwood, Mr. to Mr. Baxter (2 pages), 1945 February 14 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 83. From Russell, J. W. (4 pages), 1945 February 16 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45398 8385. Includes 2 attachments.
    - Document 84. Reconstruction Department to The Chancery (7 pages), 1945 February 19 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/50969 2947. Includes a 5 page letter to Anthony Eden from Peter Bergson.
    - Document 85. Jabotinsky, Eri to Sir Peterson (1 page), 1945 February 22 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number is undecipherable.
    - Document 86. S. of S., Colonies to Viscount Gort (1 page), 1945 February 28 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 87. Butler, M. to Mr. Jebb (3 pages), 1945 March 1-5 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 88. Gort, Viscount to S. & S. of colonies (1 page), 1945 March 3 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45376 8479. Regards Eri's arrest.
    - Document 89. Russell, John W. to The Reconstruction Department (1 page), 1945 March 5 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/50972 2985.
    - Document 90. Eastwood, C. to Captain J. M. Liddell (2 pages), 1945 March 6 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 91. From Congressional Record (3 pages), 1945 March 7 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45398 8385. Includes 1 page note from John Russell.
    - Document 92. M. B. to Sir R. I. Campbell (4 pages), 1945 March 10 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 93. M. B. to R. I. C. (1 page), 1945 March 10 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 94. Hankey, R. M. to Miss Malleson (1 page), 1945 March 13 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 95. Hankey, R. M. A. to Miss Butler (2 pages), 1945 March 13 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 96. G. to F. R. Hoyer Millar (1 page), 1945 March 31 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 97. Chancery to L. H. Lamb (3 pages), 1945 April 2 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 98. R. M. A. H. to Egyptian Department (4 pages), 1945 April 2 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 99. G. de G. to Tom (3 pages), 1945 May 5 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45399 8397.
    - Document 100. Eastwood to Sir George Gater (5 pages), 1945 May 11 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45418 8354. Includes 4 attachments.
    - Document 101. Thornley, T. H. to B. R. Curson (2 pages), 1945 May 17 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45377 2747.
    - Document 102. From Earl of Halifax (1 page), 1945 May 23 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 103. John (?) to Anthony Eden (6 pages), 1945 June 23 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45399 8397. Includes 5 attachments.
    - Document 104. Earl of Halifax to Foreign Office (2 pages), 1945 July 22 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/44537 8459.
    - Document 105. British Embassy, Washington to Consulate General (1 page), 1945 July 5 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 106. Churchill, Winston to Foreign Society (1 page), 1945 July 23 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45378 8497.
    - Document 107. Celler, Emanuel to Clement Atlee (7 pages), 1945 August 1 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45399 8397. Includes 3 page letter and 4 attachments.
    - Document 108. Balfour, Mr. to Foreign Office (5 pages), 1945 August 6 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
    - Document 109. British Embassy, Washington to Foreign Office (3 pages), 1945 August 6 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45399 (I) X/M 928.
    - Document 110. P. D. to Prime Minister (1 page), 1945 August 7 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45378 8497. Regards Weizmann.
    - Document 111. Balfour to Foreign Office (1 page), 1945 August 9 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)
    - Document 112. Hall, G. H. to Ernest Bevin (1 page), 1945 September 7 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45419 8372.
    - Document 113. Bevin, Ernest to George Hall (1 page), 1945 September 10 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)
    - Document 114. Telegram (1 page), 1945 September 15 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)
    - Document 115. Earl of Halifax to F. O., London (1 page), 1945 September 15 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45399 8397. Regards Zionists.
    - Document 116. Bentinck, Cavendish, Warsaw to C. W. Baxter, London (3 pages), 1945 September 17 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45404 8346. Regards extermination of Polish Jews.
    - Document 117. Roberts, Frank, Moscow to C. W. Baxter (2 pages), 1945 September 18 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45404 8346. Regards antisemitism by Soviet troops.
    - Document 118. Earl of Halifax to Foreign Office (3 pages), 1945 September 21 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)
      Source number: FO 371/45399 X/M 928. Regards Gillette denial of statement announcing Truman had written to Attlee asking Britain to admit 100,000 displaced Jews from Europe to Palestine.
    - Document 119. Farquhar, Mr., Cairo to Foreign Office (2 pages), 1945 September 24 (Box 15, Folder 3, Reel U11)